Beirgy to today's world, we also understand that you will eventually hear something on
our platform with which you may not agree.
While we strive to only present material that is in line with the teachings of the Orthodox
Church, we do not necessarily endorse all of the content available on our website.
Thanks for listening and thanks for your support.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever, you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st Inok, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
an hour time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism.
and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, Wranglers of Krampus.
You're listening to Lord of Spirits podcast, my co-host, Father Stephen D'Young, is with
me from Lafayette, Louisiana, and I'm Father and your Stephen Daymak, in a man's Pennsylvania,
and we are live.
So if you are listening to us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio, excuse me, and you can talk to us.
gets your calls and
second half the show and Matz is good, true, he will be taking your calls.
So the Lord of Spirits before, oh, sorry, I got started. Yeah,
before we had that disclaimer thing, the content disclaimer. Yeah.
Yes. And I do want to say, even though the opinions expressed by me
on ancient faiths, airwaves do not necessarily reflect the opinions of
ancient faith as an organization. They do reflect with 100% accuracy. And in
every
detail the personal opinions of Bobby Maddox, which is especially strange because he and I
have interacted like a handful of times. It's just weird. It's like a mirror. Yeah. It's uncanny.
All right. I'm going to read an ad now. Yeah. So the Lord Spears podcast brought to you by
our listeners. That's you people and by the Antiochian men. So the Antiochian men, which is abbreviated
Amen.
A men's ministry of the Diocese of Miami and the Southeast within the Antiochian Orthodox
Christianites Diocese of North America will be hosting the first ever Antiochian men conference
and retreat from March 7th to 9th, 2024 at the Woodland Christian Camp and retreat center in
Temple, Georgia, with a theme, the audacity of manhood strength through virtuous work.
The event will feature guest speakers, outdoor activities, sports, workshops,
fire fellowship and more.
Speakers include his great-spaceship, Nicholas,
Father Steven DeYoung.
That's me.
That's you, man.
Yeah.
That's right.
Father Hans, Jacob C. and Father Jacob Amdune.
And this event will incorporate the best aspects of camping,
conferences, and retreats into a first of its kind experience
for Orthodox Christian men, men ages 18 and older,
are welcome to register.
Early bird registration is $149 per person.
and that includes lodging for-
two nights and six meals to learn more and register go to anti-okin men.org and
click on the banner at the top that's anti-okin men.org. And here's something to
consider. I'm only in one place at a time and so at any point at any point when
I'm in a particular place that means I must consider that place cooler than
at least the other nearby available options.
Wow.
So since I am going to be at this retreat and conference, that must mean it's going to be pretty cool.
Well, I mean, it is Georgia, but in March. So...
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right. Right.
Well, anyway, tonight we're talking about technology.
This is something a lot of you people have asked us about and even though it's been discussed every so often.
often in a number of episodes, we've never dedicated a whole episode to it, and taken
that deep dive that I know a lot of you are ready for.
Now, some of our listeners may not remember this, but surely Father Steven and I remember
in 1997, when Skynet became self-aware and launched his war against the human race.
It was tough for a few years there, but later live journal and my space saved us.
So that's done.
That's it here in 2023.
perhaps more addicted to
to technology and also more afraid of it than ever before or at least in recent memory.
Will AI take over?
What happens when the robotic police force comes online?
Are we living in the matrix?
Have you or someone you know been assimilated into the board collective already?
Is transporter technology in fact a class one impossibility?
For the answers to all these questions, you will have to listen to some other podcast.
So what are we talking about anyway, father?
I will say there that could be how I get around this one place at a time issue.
Okay, get the transporter technology and get a whole Thomas Riker situation going on.
Oh, that's true. Then you'll have to wear fake glue on sideburns though.
So, well, he will, he will.
I'll be talking to Mr. Young. Yes, he will have to.
We'll call him James DeYoung, because isn't that your actual middle name?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, and then and and
you'll be slightly lower ranking
and have a different colored uniform.
That was one of my favorite bits.
And then he shows up again, right?
As one of them on a key.
I recall, right?
Deep space nine.
Yeah, that's right.
That's right.
Yeah. Good times.
Good times.
But yeah, we're not actually gonna be talking
about Thomas Ryker either on this show as much as,
they dash the hopes of many.
So what we are going to be talking about is
technology, how you define what technology is, how technology relates to how we come to
know and interact with the world, where technology comes from, is it good or bad, spoilers bad.
And then ultimately somewhere down the
line, we're going to get practical about it. Yeah, yeah. So, but as usual, we're going
to start in some somewhat rarified air, not the Neolithic era. We'll start getting back
there in the second half. But in the first half, we're actually starting kind of with
that earlier episode of the podcast.
because we need to go back and review a little as Stanley used to insist at
Marvel every issue as somebody's first issue. I really wish that weren't the case
though. I mean I know I understand there's probably some people for whom this is
the first time they've listed the podcast but it's like can you pause and listen to
a couple hundred other hours and then get to this episode if you don't mind?
Probably not.
I do, I mean the older I get the more disappointed I feel.
Now if you could create craft a voice or at least a tonality in which you could do those
little corner boxes Stan Lee used to do like see amazing spider man number 53.
The sidebar voice or way back in Avengers 47 right?
Yeah, you could you could do that but you'd have to memorize all the episode numbers.
So they added...
Cross reference those back. So I think it's easier to just review. I don't know. Okay.
fine.
At least in brief, right? And and really this episode
The questions we've gotten from folks that led up to this doing this episode started with this episode where we're referring back to
Yes, right
It is fitting in more ways than one so
The episode we did way back about the news
You
And about the different ways of knowing, we talked about
TechnA as one of the ways of knowing.
TechnA being the Greek word from which technology, for example,
and technical are derived.
And techno.
Yes, everybody's.
It's EDM now.
Oh, we don't call it techno anymore.
No, it's EDM.
I know.
What is the difference between those two?
to genres. Is there any? Yeah, I don't I'm sure there's there's there is some Gen X are out there
who can give us a discourse of the difference between techno house, industrial, EDM, right.
But I was recently informed that there's some genre called, and I'm not kidding about this, chamber pop.
And apparently it's not like a pun on chamber pot.
It's chamber pop, and it's like pop music
strings or whatever. So I could do a certain amount of genre hair splitting but
electronic music is not my forte in that regard. I am not nearly European enough
and far too affirmed in my masculinity. Getting spicy already. Yeah. We just lost
our 10 tech nail listeners.
Yes, I'm sorry, EDM listeners.
Yes.
I don't know who you were.
But yeah.
And now I'll never know.
So but.
But so take this one way of knowing amongst others that we talked about
in in that episode.
The other ones for the record were the news that we talked about
about as being a sort of spiritual
and using the term sense in a very literal way that it functions sort of like an eye and ear,
a nose if you will, right? That the news receives primarily thoughts but also potentially images,
visions right what have you from spiritual reality and we talked about a piece to me
in that episode which often gets translated as science in English which is a
type of knowledge. There's dealing with things that could be demonstrated as
in like mathematically demonstrated. This is the type of scientific knowledge
that scientific materialists say is the only type of knowledge. Yes. The kind of
knowledge. Right. Yeah. You have it. It's proven to be make a
mathematical proof, show me a repeated experiment, right, et cetera.
And then the other two are kind of related prudence, which is
Froney Seas in Greek is usually translated in English as
prudence, is sort of moral reasoning, knowing what to do in a
given situation.
Yeah.
And then wisdom, Sophia, right?
and wisdom is the ability to recognize patterns and relationships within creation.
So not patterns in the sense of what we talk about like scientific laws or something,
but just in the way that things work, being able to see those patterns and then apply them
right today.
life. And it's possible for someone to be very advanced in any one of those ways of knowing
and not be very advanced in the others. Sure. So, you know, with the news, right, you have
the monastic who has, you know, received the vision of Christ and has created glory, but
couldn't do a calculus problem to save his life.
can't quote Shakespeare, right?
Can't, you know, isn't educated in that sense, right?
Or you have people who have advanced scientific
and mathematical knowledge, but no spiritual sense whatsoever.
And you have people who are very wise,
but do not necessarily have a lot of book learning.
You have people who live very morally good lives
the world, but don't necessarily have a lot of...
You have people with a lot of book learning who are rather foolish in their personal lives and decision making
Etc. Right
And so the fifth one of these was
Tecne
Right, which at the time we defined is sort of
literally know how
Yeah know how yeah
Knowing how to do things right
Knowing how to manipulate things in the world right and
and um
to bring about certain results.
So, and again, someone can be very advanced in this,
in a particular area of this, or in general, right?
There are plenty of handymen out there,
probably handy women also, right?
You can think of an auto mechanic, right?
They may not have a lot of book learning,
but they know how to work with machines, right?
How to make them go?
Think of a pack lead.
that.
things to make us go.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
And so, one of the things that distinguishes
Tecne from these other ways of knowing is that Tecne is not
knowledge of a thing or of the relationships between things
per se.
Yeah, which is kind of questions of how things are.
Right.
So you don't have technique with regard to like an object.
Yeah. Right. You don't have
tech may with regard to a chair.
Yeah. The question with
tech is not what is it?
Right. That's not the question.
Now, tech need would be knowing
how to make a chair. Right.
Right. But knowing how to make
a chair or how to fix a chair
is not the same thing as
knowledge of the chair itself.
Or knowing how to use a chair
in an wrestling move, which I've
seen right. Which is a separate
technique.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Although almost everybody is banned,
unprotected chair shots. Yeah.
We have to take shots to the back, not the head.
I don't. I mean, you would question protocols. Yeah.
So, um, yeah. And it's not necessarily the knowledge of relationships
between things. Like when we're talking about wisdom or
prudence, prudence, you know, relations between people in terms of
Morality and and
right? Technique is not necessarily knowledge of existing relationships between things, but
it is a knowledge of the potential relationships between things. Right? So philosophical. Right?
Don't worry people. It'll get it'll it'll it'll we'll reify this a little bit. Don't worry. Yeah. Yeah. We'll get there.
We'll come back down there.
But so if you think about right there's a rock on the ground.
Right. And so you have a person who is very advanced in techniques.
There's a very skilled person.
There's a skilled worker advanced in knowing how to do things.
Right. So he may not be able to tell you exactly what type of rock it is or the mineral base
or what elements compose the rock.
Right. The way the geologist does.
Right.
and he may not be able to tell you
how that rock got there, whether it's from erosion of the surrounding area, etc.
But he can look at that rock and come up with uses for that rock.
You can look at that rock and say, well, I could fit this rock in with these other rocks to make a wall.
or this is a rock of the right size and shape and smoothness. I could use this to make
right a grinder to grind grain.
So that's technically, how can I use this object that I find?
What relationships could I put this rock into with other things in order to produce some
result?
Yeah, it's about accomplishing purposes.
Right.
So ultimately this is knowledge of how something can be...
used. How it can be manipulated, how it can be put to work. Right. That's what we're
talking about when we're talking about technique. It's an instrumental kind of
knowledge, meaning I know how I can use this thing as an instrument to accomplish
something else. Right. I know how I can use this thing. And this is true also in
in the sense of
So one of the elements, of course, when we think about this kind of knowledge is,
well, part of being able to take things that exist and put them into new relationships,
and do things with them is inventing things.
Right. Right. I mean, and we tend to think of,
like when we use the word invention or inventing,
And most of us think now about some guy with spectacles sitting up in...
his attic, creating some new machine or whatever.
And then Thomas Edison comes and steals the patent.
Yeah, exactly.
But invention at least in English
has had a longer and broader history than that.
It's often been used in literary contexts,
so like an author engages in invention.
Like he's not making some kind of device from machine,
buddy.
He's making characters, he's making situations, he's making plots, right?
But also, it applies to art as well and to philosophy, because all of this is the way
that you use whether it's language or pigment or whatever, for this purpose.
So it's not just about making a thing, it can also be about making concepts or ideas or
whatever, right?
Yeah.
existing ideas or words or whatever that already exists,
reaching them and relating them to each other in a new way. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
And it's worth noting because we've talked about how
ideas come from outside of our heads, right? In that episode of the
do's, we talked about how thoughts
come into our heads. Thoughts are like sights or sounds, right?
Sights and sounds aren't generated within our brain.
hopefully, right, barring mental illness.
But for subdates, yeah, they are received, right?
Yeah, yeah.
In the same way, thoughts are received, right?
And ideas are received.
And so this is actually included in the word invent.
Right.
And I don't even have the jingle ready.
But etymologically, and the thing is, this is one that I did not look up.
It's one that you informed me of.
I'm always happy to receive new ed.
homologies, in vents, so that vent is from, I think it's from Latin via French probably
looking at it.
But it means, you know, to come, you know, and then invent is to come in.
So the idea is that it's something that comes in.
Like, that's what literally in, in vent means is it comes in.
Right.
And so it just came to me.
Yeah.
But it doesn't, it's not created ex nihil.
Right.
Comes from somewhere else.
This is...
It already exists but it comes right it but it is brought into
existence right
Which is not exactly the same thing
As we've talked about before when we talk about
Different aspects of creation
But so
Why are we going through all this ultimately we're going we're going through this because we want to talk about technology and so
So talking about tech is to get us, try and get us to a definition.
of technology. And ultimately every product of tech name, every product of that way of knowing of
that mode of reasoning could be rightly called technology. So we tend to have a lot of arbitrary
lines in our head, right?
In terms of what's technology and what isn't.
Right.
So we tend
not to think of primitive things as technology, like the wheel, or a saddle, or a cart.
But these are things that were technological innovations at one point.
At some point in the past, this was a thing that humanity did not have, and then it had
them, and then it spread.
so
And, you know, to me, and I know I'm not going to offend anybody with this because I know we don't have any omniscient listeners because this is internet radio.
But to me, one of the basic problems with not like men and nights, et cetera, not all the end of Aptis, but with the omnis per se is
The line they draw on technology seems to me rather arbitrary.
Yeah, I mean, they're using, you know, horse drawn wagons.
technology that was technology at a certain point they're using hats
That's technology, you know, they're clearly using razors to get rid of the mustache
You're to the barn raising right that's
Technological right they did not have barns constructed in that way for most of human history, right
And so it's just a certain point is chosen and this far no farther, right
But
And we won't go past that.
But the reality is as soon as someone looks at a rock,
our technique example, right?
As soon as someone looks at a rock,
it decides to use that rock for something.
We've entered into the realm of technology.
Yeah.
They use it to build a wall.
They use it to throw it someone or hit someone with.
They use it to grind grain,
right whatever they use it for it's now technology right by the fact that they've taken it and put it to use so
Bad news to all the anarcho primitiveness out there
You can't even use rock and be consistent with your with your philosophy
There's no way to not do technology as a human
You're using stuff. Yes. Well, I mean, I guess you could just walk the earth naked and
Add
you pick directly from a plant with your bare hand.
I guess.
Please don't do that, though, people.
I don't know how long your life would last, but that's...
You couldn't come into cities because you'd be using the road or the sidewalks.
You'd have to stay out in the wilderness, right?
I'm right.
That all the time.
Right.
And so this is an important distinction to make right at the setup, because as much as I
joke at the beginning that no technology is bad.
Obviously, no one can say that all technology is bad.
Because at least not it'd be consistent.
We all wear clothing.
When it's cold, we wear warmer clothing than when it's hot,
right, et cetera.
So any broad generalization we make about technology, right?
And so, um, if...
And if we decide that the cutoff for good technology is like when I was 25, right, you could
do that, right?
As I'm very tempted to do and be old man yells at clouds, right?
Yeah.
Fine, knock yourself out.
But but the reality is that is an arbitrary line.
Yeah.
I mean, I refer to that as one's Luddite line and you can always tell when someone reach
has reached their lead-out line because they start...
referring to a piece of technology as quote, this thing.
Yeah.
That's the point at which like, oh, this far no farther.
And so we have to acknowledge that we're being arbitrary.
But people are allowed to be arbitrary if they want to.
Right?
Sure, of course.
Of course.
Yeah.
In terms of how they live their life.
And so it's also important because it's
Father Andrew Ruddup, we're not just talking about...
technology in terms of material physical implements, right? Whether we mean
hammers or iPhones. We're also talking about ideas. We're also talking about
concepts. We're also talking about narratives and world views and
Another one.
whatever other terminology like that, these are things that are formed, right?
They're formed out of pre-existing elements, right?
But we also have to be aware, and I know I've said this on the show before.
This is the infamous place where I still think I might disagree with Jonathan Pejo.
And someone asked him fairly directly in a Q&A if he disagreed with me about this.
I listen carefully to Jonathan's answer twice.
I'm still not totally sure if we disagree or not.
So we may have to hash this out in person at Pajofesta or something.
But so as we said, tech may, including when we're talking about ideas and concepts and world
views and narratives and these kind of things.
All of that, this is instrumental knowledge.
This is instrumental knowledge.
How to.
No right.
Yes.
And so because it is instrumental, this means ideas and concepts and these things are instruments.
They are not things in themselves that exist.
And therefore they don't have agency.
They can't do things.
So for talking about an iPhone, an iPhone...
can't do things by itself. You may have realized that yours is listening to you
and giving you ad recommendations based on stuff you set around it, right? But
it's still not actually the iPhone doing that. It's a piece of software installed
on your phone by a human who created that piece of software who is harvesting
your data, right? The phone itself is not the agent of this, right?
Any more than a hammer can drive a nail by itself
Any more than a gun can shoot someone by itself
Right so the concept of fill in the blank can't do anything by itself and
This is a this is a sorry atheists thing
right
Because often you will hear our atheist friends say things like
Religion is responsible for all the evil in the world
Yeah, or religion is responsible for all the wars in history.
Right.
Now aside from premafeisha being kind of ridiculously broad statements.
Religion can't do anything.
Right.
What the atheist is actually talking about there is not quote-unquote religion.
quote religion they're talking about God.
Yeah, it's it's they decided to be an atheist and don't believe it a God they can't say
God is responsible for all the words that have ever happened
They can't say God is responsible for all the evil the world because they don't believe it
So they say religion yeah, I mean you could say something like you know all the wars and look now
This is not true, but you can say some like all the wars in the world
Included religious element or are you know motivated by religion or something like that
I'm not motivated by it.
Yeah, right.
You're not motivated by it doesn't work.
Yeah, yeah, because like you can say in every war there's people have used religion right right
instrumentally, but you know yeah religion doesn't cause things
Regents cause things yeah right right so religion doesn't kill people people kill people and use religion sometimes to justify it
Various religions
Right
but religion and idea.
Right can't cause anyone to do anything
Yeah, and this is super important to
Understanding history to understanding how the world works
To helping you defeat Plato brain
Plato being the idealist of all idealists
right that and you can see this might my completely non-controvers-
the commercial example of the North American slave trade.
Right? The North American slave trade was not caused by racism.
The North American slave trade was not caused by there being
versus in the New Testament that talk about slavery that don't outright condemn it.
That idea is ridiculous and a historical.
If you look at the actual history what happened was,
People had a need to harvest.
drops like sugar cane in the new world.
The average lifespan of a worker on a sugar plantation
in the 18th and 19th century was two years.
That's how brutal the work was.
Okay, you can't hire someone to do that.
No, they're right.
Okay, they needed slavery.
Yeah, they had of course people to do it.
And after the north, the north of the lake.
slave trade began after it began. What do you see? You see in scientific circles,
scientists, these are the objective ones, right? Scientists start crafting bogus race science.
They start measuring skulls, right? They start doing all this nonsense, right? This
racial, racial, racial sites to justify what they were already doing.
Yeah, I mean, the
of especially American phenotype racism is you know crappy 19th century science.
Yes. Yes. And then you start getting you know theology also trying to
justify it as well. Right. Right. Because you have Protestants in the American
South participating in the slave trade that obviously rubs pretty rough against
Christianity.
Yeah, right? So what do they have to do yet to decide they're less than human? Yeah, what do they have to do?
They have to craft new ideas that will make it accessible
Right those ideas are instruments
Right that they used to justify themselves
But those ideas are epiphenomenal they arise after the fact
Right of what what people are doing and then get those ideas get used by people to various purposes and
And what's those ideas?
are around, right? Racism doesn't cause anyone to do anything. People appeal to racist
ideas in order to do things. Yeah, I mean, this is what motivates certain people just to
buy behavior, divide people from each other, whatever they want to do.
Yeah, I mean, we've said this in a hundred different ways now, which is that conviction follows
conditioning, you know, beliefs of whatever kind are they flow out of actions, you know,
That's it.
used to reinforce them, there's a feedback loop for sure.
But that's the way that it actually goes.
Yes.
So,
having beaten that possibly near dead horse enough,
which is just a bizarrely cruel turn of phrase too.
Is it?
Right.
Like, I don't know the origins of that one.
We can't.
He said hers.
Right. Yeah, I'm gonna look that one up.
Like we can't talk about moving on from a topic
without referring to beating horses to death
and then continuing to beat them even after their death.
But, barely comes from mid 19th century.
So roughly contemporaneous.
There we go.
They play with that.
Has anything good come out of the 19th century?
So
I guess I guess they're from the Sarah off there will answer our own question and other saints came out of the 19th century.
So in the ancient world, right, in the ancient world, we've been talking about technique. We've been using a lot of contemporary examples, right, or roughly contemporary identifiable examples.
But in the ancient world, remember, there isn't this split between material reality.
and spiritual reality. There is this sort of schism. So when we talk about technology especially,
as modern people, we are very deliberately often talking about material reality and only material
reality. In fact, a lot of the approaches to the question we're talking about tonight in general,
the question of technology and the Christian faith are approached in a way that well the
Christian faith is one thing over here and then technology and it's a spiritual thing and then there's technology this material thing over there, right?
Yeah, I mean when you say there were technology people think of computers. Yes. Yeah, and and and phones and yeah.
So, but there is not this split in the ancient world.
So, Tecne was also...
something that extended into spiritual reality. There was an idea of spiritual technology essentially.
In the ancient world. There have been several examples of this that we've talked about before on the
show. This is part of the questions we get about Techné and its relationship to some of these other
things. One of them, of course, probably the most obvious is magic. In fact, the understanding of
of technique as part of what defines.
magic per se, right over against other elements of pagan religion, right, in the ancient world.
And magic is a kind of spiritual technology that brings about a result sort of in and of itself.
Yeah, it's about the recipe. Get the recipe right and you will always get this result.
Right. You know, that the only agent involved is basically the human.
And, you know, he's just.
manipulating stuff.
Basically.
Right.
And so the same way that you have a recipe for baking bread,
and if you follow it correctly, you end up with a loaf of bread.
You have your, here's the love spell.
Here's the way to curse your enemy and give them the evil eye.
Right?
These various things.
They might sometimes involve the invocation of some kind.
of spiritual being, but it's not the invocation of a spiritual being to enter into some kind
of relationship or two-way conversation.
It's doing this will compel the spiritual being to do what you want it to do.
Yes, exactly.
Right.
Without it having any say of the matter.
So then, we've also talked about tech-n-a in a spiritual sense in regards to idolatry.
Yeah, which is, you know, since this is everybody.
race first episode. Somebody's first
episode. Somebody's okay. Everybody's
first episode. You don't have a hundred
percent turnover from episode to
episode. I don't think. Although we're
working on it, right? You try to
end as many as possible. You've got
to revolve the omnis. And everybody
who's in the house music, I think
are gone already. Edia. Yeah, I mean,
so idolatry, you know, it's the use
of images in a particular way in
order to trap and manipulate a god.
But
There is a strong sense that the God or the Spirit has agency.
Right, so there's a kind of relationship involved there.
And you know, it's funny, like, I've noticed that sometimes people I think are hesitant to think of idolatry and sacrifice to God's as being technology.
And I think that's because our modern experience of quote unquote religion is that it's this special thing you do
maybe one day a week, right? It's this special thing you do, right? But I, this was underlined
for me recently because I've been, or last week or so, I've been reading the Iliad, which in between,
you know, graphic descriptions of people's heads coming off with, because there's a lot,
a lot of fighting in the Iliad. I mean, a lot, like it is very cinematic in its detail.
Yeah, I had that. I used to have a set of Homeric Greek flashcards. And by youth, though, I mean
lies. I mean, what?
25, 30 years ago. Yeah. That's when I was first, when I was first learning classical Greek, and like
the Homeric vocabulary cards, you learn like 13 words for spear. Yes, exactly. 12 words for shield.
Learn some exciting phrases in ancient Greek, like I have judged you worthy of death. Yeah. Yeah. I
have skewered your throat with my spear. Yeah. Right, exactly. And so here's the thing that's interesting
about reading the Iliad, which it's about...
a long time since I've read it. So I really recommend this to everybody actually and the
the that's what I'm recommending Homer you go out on a limb there. Yeah, I know. I know.
Yeah, the Robert Fagel's translation is great. But what's one of the things that's interesting in
this regard about that is almost anytime one of the characters one of these heroes decides he's
going to go and take on his...
enemies or he sees them coming at him or whatever it is almost every time they will offer up a sacrifice
like it's constant I have lost count of how many sacrifices have been offered in the maybe four or
five days that have taken place in the events that I've been reading there's a lot of them and some
of them it's you know the full barbecue right and I mean literally it's talking about juicy it is
is all this kind of stuff. But in many other cases, it
It's, you know, they're filling up their cups with wine,
but they always pull out a few drops
or sometimes the whole cup to Zeus or whoever.
Right, so it's not special.
It's instrumental.
It's like we're about to do this thing.
We need this.
We want Zeus to come in.
We want all those Zeus moves who like Sassin
and his throne and laugh at everybody killing each other.
You know, we want Athena to show up.
We want Poseidon.
We want Aries.
We want Aphrodite.
It seems like he might be on the other side.
them back on ours. Yeah, it's super like tactical. It's very tactical and strategic.
These constant offering of sacrifices. So I mean, if you want to see this sense of instrumentality
in terms of sacrifice, read the Iliad. Really, I mean, it's again, I've lost count of how many
sacrifices have happened. And I'm 60% of the way through. Yeah. Yeah. For Alexander the Great,
There was no difference between you know the failings and
and offering the correct sacrifices to the correct gods
at the correct time.
In terms of how he viewed those,
these are both battle tactics.
Yeah, right.
These are both, right?
There's both technology in terms of strategy and tactics.
Yeah, yeah.
And so this is an instrumental thing, right?
It's very much instrumental.
It is getting someone to do what you want, right?
The difference then between your sort of run of the middle paganism with idolatry and sacrifice and stuff and magic is that within sacrificial ritual,
there is the idea that the God can reject the sacrifice.
Right.
And the God could decide he likes the other sacrifice better.
Other guys sacrifice better or what have you read the Iliad it's all there like this is a poem from 2700 years ago.
100 years ago, like, again, we're not.
making this stuff up. Yeah. Right and so when you start using tech, some people may have already
be ahead of at least where we're talking here. They may be thinking, well, you can not only approach
like a rock or a hammer or a piece of wood or a block of marble that you're going to sculpt or
or write a-
book you're going to write or a concept you're developing, you may not only approach that
in this sort of instrumental way, in this way of technique, but as we were just saying,
you could kind of approach spiritual entities that way, and you could also approach people
that way.
You can approach people in the sense of, how can I use this person to accomplish some
Go!
Right, and then you can instrumentalize other things like ideas
Feelings emotions, right? You can instrumentalize those things to try to get that person to do the things you want
Right to accomplish the goal
and so
when
This mode of of tech may is applied
to humans to spiritual or divine beings
It is a lately deeper
personalizing and dehumanizing.
Right, you are treating that person in the way that you would treat an object in the world.
Right, you're treating them as an object which you can manipulate and put into place.
Right, and once that begins, you've taken your first big step,
toward the idea of sort of a mechanistic cosmos.
And I say it's the first big step,
because even though they wouldn't use the word mechanistic,
because there were an ancient Greece some mechanical things,
literally mechanical things.
But they did not primarily think of those terms.
So they would talk about fatalistic might be better
be better in the classical Greek sense.
But there is a sense in which everything becomes compelled and everything becomes instrumental
and therefore free will starts to depart from the picture.
Right?
And as we move into the modern period, and the spiritual realm gets sort of caught locked off,
either separated out so it's irrelevant to the world or denied outright later on.
This becomes a kind of materialist determinism.
So I know we have some listeners at least who are at least around in contemporary philosophical circles.
This is the cause to sure is,
hey, can any philosopher out there come up up, come up with a way that anyone can have anything like free will?
Yeah.
because everything has become instrument.
Everything has become mechanical.
Everything has become clockwork. Yeah, it's all just atoms banging against each other. Right.
Such that even my right my attempts to instrumentalize the people and things around me are
just the effect of a cause that's causing me to do that.
Right. There's just sort of this endless chain with no original
instrumentalizer now, right? Because we don't even have deists anymore. There's no
original instrumentalizer whose ultimate purpose is being accomplished by this
complex chain of dominoes falling. It's just dominoes all the way down, right?
With no purpose, right? At least our Calvinist friends, I'll say something
positive. I usually pick on them. But at least our Calvinist friends
have some kind of God who kicked over the first domino and set up all the dominoes in the first place to accomplish something.
Right? So there is still some sense of meaning there, even though things then are essentially mechanistic after that.
Right, in the modern world are atheist friends.
There's not even that.
Right. And so you can no more for the majority, the majority opinion among philosophers.
Now, I think I can safely say is that there is no free will. And therefore, right, you can no
more decide what you're going to do any given day than a domino can decide which direction it's going
to fall. Right. And that's it. Everything is stagnant. Right. Everything is stagnant.
Um, um,
So, yeah, so I didn't say this was going to be a happy episode with a feel-good ending.
I never said that. Let the records show.
And a nice beat, you can dance to it.
Yeah. Now we're back to EDM. I don't...
I wasn't expecting that. We started this episode.
And all of that points to the fact that in the West, in so far as we...
I don't even like referring to the West anymore,
because I think it's a false construct.
But I mean, really what I'm meaning here
is in Western European civilization, right?
And it's airs in other parts of the world.
Tech may really triumph as a way of knowing.
I think you need look no further than secularism
and scientific materialism to demonstrate.
that has come to predominate to demonstrate that.
But it started a lot earlier than that.
So an example, atonement theories.
Atonement theories in general, the whole idea
of an atonement theory in Western European theology
is how does the atonement work?
Yeah.
like, what's the mechanism by which this happens?
How does Christ's death and resurrection work?
Yeah, right?
Yeah.
Had a very good scholar like Simon Gatherkol
when he goes to write his book,
Defending the idea of penal substitutionary atonement,
like a good Protestant does, right?
Says that the reason why that is the best atonement theory
is it's the only one with a mechanism, his word.
Wow.
So I want the mechanism that explains how it works.
That makes it the best one, right?
Which is very British, very Western European of him.
Because the only critique I'm giving
a penal substitution at tournament here,
I've got lots of them elsewhere.
But the only one I'm giving here is this idea of mechanism.
this idea that God himself must
to use some kind of spiritual technology in order to save a human being.
Yeah, you can't just do it. Right.
And the problem that comes. And this is the kind of thing you see in
Scholastic theology. I'm not just picking on Roman Catholic friends here.
is a real thing, especially in the 17th century.
That whole approach to soteriology is along the lines of this technological approach.
And this goes so far in some of the Puritans, that some of the Puritans, these are the
people who founded this country, at least according to history is written after Abraham Lincoln.
the Puritans, right, some of them.
so far as to say that if you have faith and God tries to send you to hell that you could
press a covenant lawsuit against God requiring him to actually save you because you have met the
condition of faith and that's the deal. It's just I'm dumb struck by that but I know it's real I
That's-
That's an absolutely serious theology.
Yes.
Yeah.
Now, of course, they mean this as a hypothetical.
Sure, right.
Of course.
Right.
They don't think God is going to try to,
they wouldn't say God is going to try to damn anyone who has faith, right?
Right.
But...
Yeah, there's this dog.
Think about it that way.
Yeah.
Ideas arise from somewhere, right?
What makes that thought thinkable to them
is the mechanistic way in which they're viewing.
Salvation. Yeah, right. Yeah, that is a thought that had never occurred to most of our listeners. I'll bet
Never approach salvation quite that way right
From that angle
And of course, right as we said a fiestic materialism
You would be on other there are other forms of materialism. I worry sometimes when we talk about materialism
on the show that a bunch of things are getting slurried together.
Sure.
Yeah, I remember when I was a kid growing up in mostly kind of Baptist and Baptist adjacent
type churches, materialism was a word that meant possessiveness, you know, being into stuff,
you know, basically like Madonna, being a material girl.
Yeah.
Yeah, so we're not talking about greed or consumerism.
Right, right, per se. Right. I mean, that's obviously not completely unrelated, but
And we're not talking about dialectical materialism
Right, we're not you know, I don't think anyone would tune into this show for analysis and critique of Marx's Dost copy tall
I would
But it's not what I thought before.
Yeah, I don't think we get even.
What episode out of that?
Like halfway through the episode, it would just be a little blog and be like why?
Right, but we're talking about atheistic materials. It means or scientific materialism
Essentially the belief that only things that are materially complied composed exist. Yeah again, Adam's banging against each other
Yeah, anything that is it is a thing. Yeah, anything that isn't materially composed does not exist
But that idea, obviously, if you have that idea, then you can see how you end up with
no free will.
You can see how everything is just mechanical interrelations and cog wheels.
And you can see this, back to picking on the 19th century again, in the rise of social
sciences.
the idea of social sciences. The idea that there is some science to the way in which an individual human works.
Right. Some kind of mathematical formula, some kind of discoverable pattern and mechanism.
And then when you look at things like sociology, larger things, how humans work in groups and groups work.
Right. Why are we trying to find the technique of these things so that we can manipulate them so
so that we can change.
them so that we can instrumentally get them to do what we want.
Right.
I mean, a lot of people are doing that in a theoretically well-meaning way, although not all of them.
Yeah.
Historically, definitely not all of them.
Historically, usually not.
Yeah.
There are a lot of them.
There may be, there may, listen, may be some do-go-to-social engineers now.
But historically, social engineers in eugenesis work work.
are not the good guys. But what you end up there, right? Because, and people have probably heard
this, right? What's the debate about people's behavior? Like we're going to talk about crime.
Where does crime come from? Is it from nature or is it from nurture? Let's pause and think about
about that second.
Those are the only two options.
It's either in
nature. It's their genetics. They're born that way. Right? And so if you come down on that side,
that's where you get eugenics. Yeah. We need to stop having people be born that way.
We need to get them to be born another way. We need to get rid of all the people who are born
that way and or not let them reproduce. All the horrors almost all the horrors of the 20th century
right there. Right? And if you want the rest.
of the 20th century, then on the other side are the people who decide it's
nurture. It's their environment. Right? Therefore we must re-engineer society to
create the new man. Right? We can socially engineer this and give people these
experiences and these structures that will create a different kind of person.
And we'll put an end to this.
Here comes tyranny, right?
For your own good, right between those two poles, right?
But those are the only two ways for humanity to improve.
Once you embrace this kind of scientific materialism and this instrumental technological view
of the world, those are the two options you have.
Those are the two poles you have to bounce.
between. Right? And so in many ways, although the enlightenment wanted to cast itself as an
enlightenment as we're going to throw off the darkness of the dark ages, we're going to
get rid of all of this Christian nonsense and get to science and knowledge and reason, right?
all these good things.
It's not a coincidence that this went hand in hand with a return to pagan literature
Right pagan art
Because it is essentially a revival of the same worldview that was held by paganism
Yeah, the term mystic fatalistic
Mechanistic and manipulable. I don't know. Yeah
Yeah, it will be manipulated.
Yeah, I mean...
It's in so many ways the Enlightenment is essentially a kind of reframing of paganism,
but now instead of God's named Zeus and Odin or whatever, it's God's named progress
and whatever else.
Yes.
The economy.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, it's not gonna get
much happier from here guys. I'm warning. This is like the end of season two of Battlestar Galactica.
Like it's going to get a lot worse before it gets any better. The one with Lauren Green or? No.
No, I know. I know. That was the happy, nice Battlestar Galactica. Those were the friendly
moments in space. Our star book was still a guy. Yeah. All right. All right. Well, that's sad. We're
We're gonna go ahead and take our first break and
and we'll be right back with the second half of this episode of The Lord of
Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
What are we to make of the unseen world and spiritual
Warfare. The Lord of Spirits, book version, is now available at store.ancientfaith.com,
written by Father Andrew Stephen Damick. To the modern mind, dragons and demons are just the
inner demons of psychology. And angels are often reducible to the better angels of our nature,
That is to our better human impulses and virtues.
Talk of spirits is really about psychology.
But to the ancient mind of millennia ago, even up to the pre-modern mind of just centuries ago,
these are real beings with personal presence, who inhabit our world, and affect us.
Father Andrew provides a distillation and
explanation of the material in the popular podcast The Lord of Spirits, which he co-hosts with Father Stephen D'Young.
Get this brand new book today at store.AncientFaith.com.
store.angianfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Yeah, everybody should buy that book.
Yeah, we're kind of preaching to the choir on this one.
I know, but I mean, you know, these are the people we're gonna...
You know that your new book is...
based on the podcast that you host with me. I've heard that. Yes. I wish I could remember the name.
I know. But you know, I mean especially for people for whom there is this is their first episode
since we've talked to them and about these times. Yes. That book might help you out everybody.
You don't I'm not saying don't listen to all the 200 plus hours of other stuff. But if you're
If you're looking to jump in, that book could probably help you do that.
You know, that's one of its purposes.
So yeah, and as somebody who has like 163 hours into Baldur's Gate 3,
I don't know who you are who's complaining that that's too much to listen to.
It's true.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't know how you find Father Andrew, but I am at least as entertaining as that game.
So anyway, welcome back everybody.
It's the second half of this episode of Laura Spirits. We're talking about technology and
As we just said in the first half
It's about instrumentalizing in all the ways that that means
so
Speaking of the ancient world
Where did all come from?
Where will it go take us back? Oh
Oh yeah, so now we're going back to the
not quite the Neolithic era, we're not going back quite that far. Mainly because we don't have
anything written from that because there wasn't writing. No, we have rocks and scratches and
some tombs. Yeah. And so while there was technology, as we already mentioned, right,
there was a technology. So to somebody figured out a way to tie a rock onto the end of a stick and
can make a spear, right?
which are depicted in those early cave paintings, technology, we don't know, we don't have the stories from those people in terms of how they understood the origin of technology.
Yeah, we don't know what they thought about it. We don't have, I mean, it is a true dark ages, right, in the sense of, yeah.
which that was the original meaning of that everybody by the way is that it was
a period where there wasn't much literature being produced. That's all that
really meant.
was so we sort of get back to it in the published right so we don't know that much about that it wasn't like
All is dark and evil and you know whatever and ignorant rules everyone
Which is how we depict it now at least how the enlightenment often depicted you know
So yeah
Yeah, I imagine when they first started making like metal-bladed knives there was some guy
With like a sharp rock going like these kids, you know
Um.
But we don't know that for sure. Yeah, exactly. He didn't write anything.
Yeah, so we actually so by the way, we actually do have someone
calling in that has a question about magic. So
Joseph, are you there? Can you hear us?
Yes, hi fathers. Welcome. Welcome to Laura's Spirit's podcast for hopefully this is not a deck building question because I'm not really
Yeah, thank you, fathers for having me.
So yeah, my question is tangentially related to both, I think, technique and magic.
And I hope I phrased this correctly.
But in a previous episode, it was mentioned, I understood correctly, that magic was understood as a way to sort of force the gods to do what you wanted them to do.
And it was using a certain formula.
So.
What, I guess my question has two parts.
How would you explicitly differentiate magic from technique
and then also connected to the formula aspect?
What differentiates, I guess, the eucharistic prayer
and divine liturgy, since it uses the same phrasing
on a weekly basis, like how would you differentiate that
from magic since we're...
attempting to get God to bless, you know,
offering every week.
Yeah.
Well, okay, so there's a couple things I'll say.
Number one, magic is a subset of technique.
So it's a particular kind of instrumentalization.
Okay.
And the point is that if you do it right,
then you always get a certain result.
It may involve trying to force gods
You
stuff, but it may not. It also may be just sort of about, you know, manipulating the elements
of the world, you know, that kind of thing. And yeah, it's, this is a good question you
ask about the Eucharist, right? Because I think especially for those of us who, even if
we don't have a Protestant background, we live in a Protestant country, in a lot of ways,
a country with what's left of a Protestant culture maybe.
And at least American Protestantism is not that ritualistic in its worship.
So it tends to present itself in a much more kind of informal way.
And so therefore when you see complex worship, people sometimes look at that and say you're
doing magical spells, right?
Because of the complexity of it, right?
But here's the really important thing.
because there's a
It's a complex method to something.
Does not make it magic.
Magic is about guaranteed results
and about the actions themselves doing the thing.
The Eucharist is explicitly a request,
a prayer to God to do something.
Right, he does not have to do it.
Now he is the one who himself gave it.
I mean, we see that in the gospels.
gives the Eucharist to us to do and commands us to do it.
So this is not something that we dreamed up to make, to force God to do anything.
This is something he gave us to do, something he is doing that he's inviting us to participate
in and tells us how to do that.
Right, so it's not magic because it doesn't happen because the priest does the technique
right.
Which is why, for instance, variations between Eucharistic liturgies that exist between
traditions or...
sometimes represent completely other rituals, right? So the the the Eucharistic
liturgy of the Byzantine tradition is quite different from the Eucharistic
liturgy of the Latin tradition, even prior to the Great Schism, they are quite
different from each other, and yet they still both were the Eucharist. If it was
magic, then the technique would need to be essentially the same, right? Because if
you're going to get the thing to do, what you want it to do, you have to follow the
recipe. That's how it works. Right. So yeah, it's about
asking God to act, it's not about making God do anything. As if we could, right?
That's not a thing. You can't force God to do anything. So that's what I would
have to say about that. I don't know, Father, you got anything to add or adjust
or um, actually. Well, in terms of the Eucharist, the Eucharist falls within the
realm of sacrifice, right? And sacrificial worship, right? So now I'm talking
in the general sense.
So, sacrificial worship of the general sense, which includes the Eucharist, includes pagan
animal offerings, includes sacrifices in the Old Testament, right, sacrifice broadly.
Has always included within it the idea, this is what differentiates it from magic, that
the God can reject the sacrifice.
And this was literally institutionalized in the ancient pagan world.
This is why you would have a horoscopes.
Harusbex is somebody, Harusbex is the Latin word, but this kind of activity predates Rome
by a lot in the ancient areas.
But Harusbex is a particular type of priest who practiced expacy, which is the reading
of the entrails of a sacrifice animal.
So his whole job, and we have like mocked up kidneys and lungs.
and things that have inscriptions on them,
like made of stone, with inscriptions in them,
that were used to train herospixes,
a herospicies, I guess.
In their art form, so after the animal was sacrificed,
they would go in and get into the guts of the animal
literally and look for signs as to whether
the god had accepted the sacrifice or not.
Right, and so if they found, you know, black spots on certain organs.
or we have records in some cases of organs being missing.
Right? They go in there and one of the major organs, like a heart in one case, is missing.
This was taken as this horrible omen that, oh no, the gods have rejected the sacrifice.
Right? And then you would have to come up with some other actions to figure out why and
then to try to, you know, offer more sacrifices and get them back on your side. Now, obviously
we've Christians don't do all that activity, but the existence of that and the prevalence
So that's it.
shows that unlike magic there is this possibility that even if you do everything right, it might not work.
Which means that the divine still has its agency.
In the Old Testament, we find this, you know, gets to the point in the prophets where God tells them to stop offering the sacrifices.
Because he says you know your hearts are far from me
You're behaving however you
want and then coming and offering sacrifices like that makes it okay. Like I have to
then forgive you even though you're not repentant. Right. That's not how this works.
Right. So God makes clear through his prophets of the Old Testament that he
retains his autonomy. Right. Sacrifice it is not what operating this mechanistic
way. And even within some of the prayers of the Eucharist. Right. So for example
Well, in the leadership of St. Basil the Great, I pray a prayer.
It's often done.
silently. So everyone may not hear it. But I pray a prayer asking God not to withhold the grace of the Holy Spirit from the gifts because of my sins as a priest.
Yeah, which suggests that that's a thing.
Yeah, that suggests that that's a possibility, right? That is within it, acknowledging the possibility that God could say to me or to my congregation, or to some portion of the church,
what he
said to ancient Israel. No, stop. Repent first. Right. Um, so that that is a, that is a
live possibility there. Um, what I'm about to say is not me taking a cheap shot at our Roman
Catholic friends. It is me trying to avoid taking a cheap shot at our Roman Catholic friends.
I think this would be a worthwhile question about the Eucharist to ask to an
informed Roman Catholic person.
Because I know the whole focus, focus thing,
I know they have a good answer for that.
I am not the person equipped to answer that for them
and explain the difference from their perspective.
Because there is very much within the Roman Catholic
theology of ordination and how they see that as working
and the carisms granted to a priest,
a kind of mechanistic view of this.
if he grabs bread and wine and says the words of institution, they automatically become the body and blood of Christ.
You can find theological statements that talk about the Roman Catholic priest reaching up into heaven and compelling Christ to come down.
So that would be a good question to ask them. I'm sure there are answers from a Roman Catholic perspective.
I'm not the one equipped to give them and so I don't want to caricature them here.
But if you do get the opportunity to ask somebody,
uh, Robert Gavick, and that's somewhere,
I'd be interested in reading it, their answer.
So, yeah.
All right.
Does that, uh, answer your questions, Joseph?
Yes.
Thank you, fathers.
All right. Thanks for calling in.
Okay, Doug.
Well, we're not going neolithic, but, you know,
you know, lithic? No. Not even, and definitely not paleolithic.
Yeah.
Post-slithic.
What is our relationship to those raw?
We're going Bronze Age.
Okay, yeah.
Hey, that's the elite again.
Yeah.
Everything in that thing is Bronze.
That's, but we're even earlier, we're, we're, we're all earlier than the, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Bronze Age.
I won't go down that rabbit trail now about why everything is broad.
But anyway, because it was actually written in the Iron Age.
But yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So we're going back to, and this is a story we've referred to,
really a set of stories, set of Babylonian stories that we've
referred to before from the original Babylonian empire.
So we're talking about the middle of the second millennium BC.
not the neo-Babalonean Empire.
The Babylonian Empire that you,
we meet in the Bible with Nebuchadnezzar,
and his Namo Palacere and those folks.
That's the neo-Babalonean Empire
that takes Judah into exile.
This is the original Babylonian Empire,
middle of the second century BC.
I was about to try to date it in terms of biblical events,
but I'd have to weigh it on the date of the Exodus
there are a few.
Don't jump in.
Believe it or not.
And this is the story of the Opkalu or the Seven Sages.
Right.
A Toppo or a Dapa in his buds.
Who are, as we've talked about before,
sorry with a Dapa who's sort of a fish person.
Supernatural being.
who emerges from the rivers.
comes and he's called a sage because he comes in any parts wisdom to the rulers. He's
followed by six other sages. When you look at King's lists from this period, right, the
Kings before the flood have these upkallu, these sages as their advisors, right, and that
sort of why they are able to become King. They have this wisdom from the spiritual realm
spiritual beings. And then as we've talked about before after the flood, the Kings are said to be
two-thirds of the Apollo that there's this sort of interbreeding represented within the story.
But the Apollo proper from before the flood, they end up in prison beneath the rivers
in the abyss by the gods for having given this knowledge to man but the
importance of the function of this story in the middle of the Second Millennium BC for the Babylonian Empire.
This Babylonian Empire was established by the Amurru, which literally means the Westerners that came from what's now Syria.
Hamarabi, being the most famous one, who's a king during this period, they used this story in large part to justify their own reign.
that they claimed to still have this secret wisdom. Yeah, this is given.
It does. Yeah, Colleux.
Anti-deluvian knowledge. Yeah. Yeah.
They claimed to still have this.
And of course, as we've mentioned before on the show, the Amurru are the biblical amurites.
That giant clan. Right.
probably the most famous one being
Cihon of
organ
Cihon.
I say more probably the most famous because he's the one we sing about at Christmas.
Yeah, or in I think in all of the, um, why am I blanking on my liturgical language now?
The poliole.
Polyelia.
There you go.
That's right.
Yeah.
It's not Christmas until org has been slain.
That's not one of my Christmas ornaments actually.
I will stand by the if you ever find
a dead aug Christmas ornament. Send it to me.
Oh man, I mean, it will have pride of place.
Or to say, now that we live in this age
where you can literally just order up
any kind of merch with anything on it.
Yeah.
Even if you just have the 3D printer plans
like the file, send that to me, of dead aug Christmas ornament.
You're gonna get a hundred of those.
I'm just saying cool. I am so fortunate.
You can have an entire Og Christmas tree.
My wife has the miniature paints, right?
We'll mix in some more Hammer 40K.
It'll be all good.
Nice.
Take pictures, post them on the.
Yeah.
On the.
So, right, so this is sort of this.
Right, now remember, we have to always remember.
The earliest written thing we have was very likely
not created out of whole cloth.
So the upholster is not the origin of anything.
We can't say that, because there's
untold amounts of ancient literature
that either didn't survive or is
in a cupboard at the British Museum somewhere untranslated.
So we don't know.
We can't construct an origin.
But this is our earliest...
So far known version of this story.
And this version of this story, by the way,
didn't become widely known until about 2010.
Like journal articles started being published
about the translation of these tablets
from which the Apollo stories come around 2010.
So 13 years ago.
Right.
So who knows what's still out there
and what we'll learn in the future.
But this is at least a representation,
middle of the second
the Millennium BC about the origins of technology, right, about the origins of this kind of
technique, kind of knowledge, right. And we see just as, and we've talked about this a lot,
as we see in the scriptures, we see sort of the God-given take, right, out of the
like the flood. Right? We see in Genesis the God given take of this kind of story. Right? And
this is in the period leading up to the flood, particularly associated with the line of
Cain as it plays out in his genealogy, especially at the end of his genealogy in Genesis 4.
Yeah, so the ends being...
Lemic.
Yeah.
Not the same guy that's the father of Noah.
No.
It just has the same name.
Apparently it was a common name.
Yes.
From the last interdeluvian generation.
Yeah.
So okay.
So Genesis chapter 4 verses 19 through 24.
And Lemic took two wives.
The name of the one was Adah, and the name of the other was Zilla.
Adah bore Jabal.
He was the father of those who dwell in tents and have livestock.
His brother's name was Zhu-
ball. He was the father of all those who played the liar and pipe. Zilla also bore
tubal cane. He was the forerger of all instruments of bronze and iron. The sister of tubal cane
was Naama.
Lemek said to his wives, Aadah and Zilla, hear my voice, you wives of Lemek. Listen to
what I say. I have killed a man for wounding me, a young man for striking me. If Cain's
This revenge is 7-fold and LAMMIX is 77-fold.
The first person who's a polygamist in the Bible,
for anyone still unclear on what the Bible thinks about polygamy,
it sings this song to his wives about how great he is.
Remember Cain's revenge being sevenfold.
That was the revenge God was going to take for Cain.
So when Lammix is 77fold, he's saying actually he's greater than God.
fear him more than God. Nice fella. Not a good look. So the key part here is these three
sons, right, and what they create, right? So the first one, Jabal is the father of those who
dwell in tents that have livestock and you're like, well, what's wrong with living in a tent?
That's not the problematic part. It's the livestock part.
Yes, it's the hoarding of wealth because, you know, a hunter gatherer society, everyone
has equal access to the food.
Well, not well, you missed a piece there, Father Andrew.
Oh, excuse me.
They're not supposed to be eating animals yet.
Oh, well, there's that as well.
Yes, that's true.
Yeah, right?
So, but still.
They haven't been given permission to eat animals.
And so what does this represent?
This is an element of God's...
creation that they have chosen to instrumentalize.
Yeah, they're just taking it and controlling it and using it.
And using it. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
It's a very different relationship with animals than what Adam had when he named them.
Right. Yep.
Raising them for slaughter. So there's a shift. And that's technology. Right.
learning how to breed
raise, kill, butcher, cook, eat, right?
Animals,
Jew balls, probably all those who play the liar in pipe.
This is saying music is bad.
No, it's not.
It's also not why we don't use instruments in liturgy.
Although I have at least once heard somebody try to argue that.
Wow.
Right. So the liar end of the pipe is translated here.
The idea here is that this is a particular type of music.
This is a type of music used in pagan festivals and pagan rights.
And so this is actually a kind of spiritual technology that they're talking about him devising.
Right.
and then two ballcane.
Who was everyone knows from the Noah movie got into an epic fist fight with Noah on the deck of the arc during the flood?
I still haven't seen that. Is it worth it?
Well, it depends on what you mean by worth it.
Okay, okay. I was I feel compelled to watch all these things and I was much more entertained by that one than most of them.
Okay. Okay. But I emphasize the word entertain.
entertain.
Yeah, yeah, I got in.
informed intergrade. Right. It's a thing. Yeah. And no, it is not
yell, are you not entertained just for the record, even though it
is. Rosal crow. Yeah.
During the fist fight. And hey, you've got Anthony Hopkins as
Methuselah, so hang me around.
Watch the
movie to see how you can go wrong. But Tubal Kane, he's the forger of instruments
of bronze and iron. Right? Again, bronze and iron tools. Yeah.
So that's the old, but this is right. Why is this? What's the first thing you do when
you learn metallurgy? Weapons? Yeah, you kill people. Weapons for killing people.
So we see that Kane's like, we're not going to read the whole genealogy.
as exciting as that would be.
But Cain's line that culminates here, right? You can see there's this descent
Right
There's a descent from Cain pun here, but
It it descends downward it gets worse
right and
This decline was not seen by for example second temple Jewish interpreters as being accidental
Right. Josephus, for example, portrays cane as...
the archeratech, the one who teaches sin.
He teaches sin and wickedness to his children.
Yeah, he's not just like, oh, poor Cane,
he made a big mistake and now he's out.
Yeah, but he remained actively evil.
All right, he's a villain.
Yeah, right.
And so this continues, right?
And it's out of this descent, right?
That we see this technology emerging.
Right.
Out of the descent technology comes, we don't read about technology coming from Seth's
line, leading up to Noah.
So this means that while the up-caloo story is casting as this positive thing, this coming
of divine knowledge, this is a great thing that gives the right to rule, right, and brings
glory to a civilized
We see quite the opposite here, right?
The technology is actually coming from the worst of the worst, right?
And represents a descent into evil.
In the Genesis account, though, it's, of course, as we've talked about several times on the show,
and we won't go back and do again as much as it might excite people.
This is the supernatural element of this is at least hinted at.
or point
to in Genesis 6, 1 through 4 in terms of the Nephilim. In the expanded version of this story that you get,
for example, in Firstean-Edg or the Book of Jubilee's, this is made sort of even more clear that these,
it's both, both gives further description of what the Tegnese is that is received by the line of
cane and makes it explicitly clear that
It's clear that this is being revealed by demonic powers, by specifically fallen wicked spiritual
powers.
So, again, very similar to the Apollo story, but in a way, inverted.
It's not, these are the good guys bringing wisdom to man and God or the gods are the bad
guy sort of punishing them and ruining it.
everybody's party. That's the pagan version of the story.
Right, right, but quite the opposite, right, quite the opposite, the exact
inversion of that. Right. And so in the versions we find in the book of
Enoch and the book of Jubilee's, right, amongst the
technique that's taught is sorcery. This, of course, in Greek is
as we've said before, which is a
And again, an instrumental means to enter into and manipulate the spiritual realm,
seduction, and implements of seduction, like an eye makeup, literally, in the public.
Yeah, I mean, cosmetics are part of this bundle of technology used to destroy people.
the arts of seduction and again we have to remember
arcs of seduction. In this case, there is the element here heavily of pagan ritual, right?
Think about the alpahor. Right. And what goes on there is we've talked about in the book
of numbers. Yeah. And there's Thomas Dolby. She blinded you with science. There's, there's
there's so bestiality stuff in there.
There's, but there's also.
So that pagan sexual ritual element, right?
It wasn't just, you know, the beguiling of daudiness.
It was just that sexual morality is bad.
Yes it is, right.
But within this context, this is women receiving this from a demonic being with whom they have
an intimate relationship, right?
so that other element that...
spiritual element is always present. And of course, divination. Right. Yes.
Which is one of the things that's listed trying to tell the future by observing
things. Yeah. Yeah. But one of the things that we may not think about, right? And
you know, this isn't just a wordplay. It's a deliberate word choice, right? Is that
divination is a way of determining the...
future. In the sense that if I know it, if I know what is going to happen tomorrow, then that means it is determined.
Yeah. Right. So divination was understood not just as a way of, hey, I'm curious, you know, what horse is going to win the fifth race tomorrow so I could place a bet. Right.
But this is a way of
locking it in, right? Locking it into place, right? It's not just satisfying a
curiosity. We need to keep that in mind like with the story of Saul on the
Witch of Endor. Right, when he goes before battle, it wasn't just, hey, is this
gonna go well or is this gonna go badly? Because if you say badly, maybe we won't
fight, right? Or we'll do something else because he's told it's gonna go badly and
he fights anyway. Yeah, right. It's an attempt to try to lock into place the
result.
that you want. Yeah. And, and you know, there's a gazillion ways that this gets done. Like
you mentioned the harrow specks earlier, you know, examining the innards of slaughtered
animals. But like another one, again, from the Yili, lots of ornithomans, or nithomansi,
or nithomansi. Yeah. Yeah. Telling the future by observing birds, also known as aucary.
there's a loro mancy which is cats
There's a mere momancy, ants.
I mean, there's so many possibilities.
Yeah. Anything that can form patterns.
Yeah. Yeah.
You could find someone who claimed to be able to read the patterns.
And it's a specialist. Like, it's a technologist who's able to do this theoretically.
Right. Right.
And before we move on from the divination thing,
did you know there is both an episode of I Dream of Genie and an episode of Bewitched
in which they...
accidentally
Magic up the next day's newspaper. I
Did not know that and at hilarity and so's involving betting on horses
Huh, and isn't that
Isn't isn't Barbara Eden in both of those? No, no no my gummeries in bewitched. Come on
I'm sorry. I'm sorry
Sorry, I was distracted thinking about Marmato Mansi, which is what you see in yeah
Marbeth?
Oh, you know, punk Satani Phil right here in Pennsylvania.
But this whole this whole this whole but which thing man not only have you let me down.
I think you've let yourself down.
You probably don't even know which one's Dick York and which one's Dixargent do you?
I'll go sit in the corner and you can just monologue for the rest of the good.
We don't have to go that far. Okay. Okay. That's
Although one more infraction now it's been years since I was
either one of those shows, but
Nick at night is no longer like a big part of my life. Well, I'd nick it night now is showing shows from like the 90s
Oh, just get depressed. It feel old.
You know, apparently now like the stuff that we listen to the 80s is quote
oldies
Yeah, that's offensive to me. I'm sorry. Oh, yeah, man
Everything we listen to in the 90s is now classic rock
a-ha-ha-ha-ha.
A-ha-ha-ha-ha-ha.
Fold the starting to powder.
So let's talk about Prometheus.
Yes, let's talk about something older than us.
Yeah.
So yeah, so there are obviously other places.
We talked about the, the, I'll probably
sort of sort of being a preceding version of this story
from the biblical narrative.
the versions that we have at least
of certain Greek stories.
the versions we still possess are later the biblical account, but we see similar parallels
right, even within the pagan versions of these stories. So for example, Prometheus,
right, is in some places identified as a Titan, right? And so his narrative sort of fits into
the Titan narrative, the overarching Titan narrative. And also can I just say the most ironically
name.
guy ever. I mean his name means for thought. I'm like, yeah, exactly. Did you really?
The, anyway, sorry. We've talked before the show about how the tight narrative, the tightens
and being a prison in Tardarus is sort of associated in the Second Temple Jewish period. And even
even in the scriptures themselves, in the New Testament, scriptures themselves, with the rebellious
angels from before the flood who are imprisoned, right? St. Peter actually used...
the word Tartarus for the place where they're imprisoned. And so he's sometimes referred to as a
Titan. We could see there's a similar pattern, right? But of course he famously brings fire to humanity,
right? The knowledge of fire, this brings about his punishment, right? By the gods,
right, but what gets off and left out because again
even bizarrely pagan myths are read in a materialist way is that the the
particulars and you can find this in Hesse the particulars of what fire is
referring to here right because that could refer to a lot of things he brings
fire to man the ability to give them a lot of fire right like right yeah the way
it's often depicted is like it's like he gives them a lighter like here's how
make campfire guys here's a torch
let it go out, keep other things lit.
Right. No, no, it's, it's yeah, like he's, I mean, we've made references on the show before,
the whole burning the bones thing where, yeah, where, you know, mankind gives the garbage
parts of the, of the sacrifice to the gods. It's per metheists who, who teaches them how
to do this. It's like, okay, but that's the bones and then take the fat and put that
on. So Zeus won't see that you're not giving him the stakes and burn that as a sacrifice
to him and meanwhile
you keep the stakes.
Like that's an element of what giving fire to mankind
is really about.
Right.
The fire here is talking about sacrificial technology.
Yeah.
And this is why the gods get mad.
They're not like, oh, they can cook their meat.
No.
No, it's.
Or hey, they're setting themselves on fire.
They would have thought that was funny.
Right.
Especially kind of gods they are.
But he was a doth are setting each other on fire.
Ridiculous.
It's because of this element, right?
This is now there's this bothersome thing going on vis-a-vis the gods themselves.
You know, right that that makes them that makes them mad.
Right. The gods really care about themselves.
They care about their demigod kids and they don't care about pretty much anybody else.
Right. Unless Zeus finds you attractive and then you're in real trouble.
Right. They don't love you unless they love you and then that's not good.
Yeah. Zeus never understood that no means no.
Um.
So, uh...
While we're at it
Time apparel we've talked about Prometheus or at least mentioned Prometheus before in this context of the show
I don't think we've mentioned Cicifus
No in this context before if people know about him
They know he's the rolling the rock up the hill guy. Yes, which he is yes, right, but there's a lot more to it and
You know can move hand that I am
Cicifus
If you actually read the stories about cis.
There's a couple different versions, by the way, that have been passed down to us.
But, Cicifus is the king who founded the City of Corinth.
The Old Corinth.
Yes. And is a bad guy.
So, let's say Corinth is, is that, Corinth is the city you go to if you really want to have a dark monitor out.
Yes, exactly.
But so he's he he founded Corinth the first part
his story where he forese comes to the God's attention as it were, is he has this brother
he wants to kill, his brother who he wants to kill. But it was widely understood, even among
pagans, that you commit murder within families. That's how you get fury showing up and dragging
you to Hades. Nobody wants that. So he went to the Oracle at Delphi.
to ask Apollo through the Oracle at Delphi to give him a technique where he could
murder off his brother without incurring like wrath.
And I'm getting big ghost vibes here.
Yeah.
Well, so there's some of that.
There's also some cane vibes here.
Yeah.
Right.
No, my brother don't want to get killed in response, right?
Um, and then the, the second part of his story where he gets in trouble is that he was
apparently renowned for visitors, travelers, strangers who pass through Corinth.
He wouldn't murder and take their stuff.
Also the other big rule you're not supposed to violate it, and he's in pain in his hospitality.
Right.
Um, but here, here we get some lamic of vibes.
Yeah.
Right, I've killed a young man for-
wronging me, I have healed it. But what finally, because of those two things, right, the gods
killed him, right? But here's how good of a technologist, Cisophis was. So depending
on the version of the story, either a Thanatos or Hades, right? One of those two gods
is responsible for change.
him up in the underworld, right? Because of this bad stuff he did. And Sisyphus talked in this story,
talked either Hades or Thedatos into explaining to him how the chains worked. I mean, I can see this
is like a scene in a sitcom or something, right? Hey, how do these chains of death work, by the way?
So they explain it to him and he figures it out.
Yeah.
So not only does he get...
lose, but he chains up Hades or Thanatos. Yeah, which has the effect of makes a break
for it, making it so that nobody can die. Right. So nobody dies. And then in the Hades
version of the story, this makes Aries very mad because he's got wars going on and nobody's
dying. That's no fun. And that's the thing he's into. Right. That's like his whole bit.
Right. In the Thanatos version of the story, because of the nature of Thanatos, as a
out of death.
talked about this before on the show, but no one can die, meaning like the sick and the wounded
and the infirm and the elderly can't die. So they're just sort of lingering and suffering.
Right. Either way, right, someone comes either Aries in the one version or where the other
God's in the other version and lets the death God loose again and Cicophus ends up in Tardar
is pushing the rock up the hill.
Yeah, which rolls down is...
as soon as he gets it up there and he has...
Rolls down every night.
And he has to put your back up.
It's futility.
Yeah, it's a futile labor.
Futile labor, not futile labor.
He's not far from you.
He's on a surf.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so yeah, I mean, other mythic traditions
have gods who function in some of these ways
of giving knowledge to mankind, secret knowledge, right?
And there's different versions of it, but like none of them are quite exactly for me at the US,
but I mean, a lot of it is just variations on the theme.
But one of the things that's interesting to me is the kind of the second tier of this that you get,
especially in, like you get in Germanic mythology particularly, which again, you know, remind everybody,
Germanic mythology comes to us through Christians who wrote it down.
often centuries out.
after the last pagan in their area was baptized, right?
The last great pagan tradition, get baptized.
And so, it's mediated through that.
And so what you get then is,
sort of these lesser spiritual beings,
not titans or whatever, right?
It's kind of lesser spiritual beings who have knowledge,
but it's often not in terms of giving knowledge to people
so that they can rule,
but rather providing them with cool stuff.
And so that's where you get this whole realm of like Smith God.
right. So my favorite is Whalan to the Smith who's actually sort of sort of divine
and in dramatic paganism he's often the guy who makes whatever impressive
sword or a bit of armor that's around in the story is often said to be from Whalan
that he's the guy who made it or Veylon depending on where you are or
Voland you know same guy but then you also get like dwarves you know again
and like they're making...
magical stuff, especially magical weapons.
But then you also get, like, Whalen, for instance, becomes a tutor figure.
Like gods will send their sons to him to go so they can learn stuff from him.
So he still functions in that same way.
But this idea, right, of the kind of the divine mediator of technology is still a thing.
Even though now it's kind of demoted a little bit within some of these more marginal
mythologies and by marginal
I don't mean that they're not important.
I mean, marginal sense of like being long distance away
from the ancient areas where the Bible arises and so forth.
Yeah.
And this is not the wayland of Wailen Utani Corp, by the way.
Where do you mean the way?
Could be.
No, it's not.
I appears to play it anyway.
Nevermind.
So, right.
And of course, if you...
We want really post biblical is in recent, right?
Not comparatively.
This is an enduring story about technology.
Yeah, right.
Probably, I don't know anymore.
I'm about to go on a grumpy old man rant
that'll stop myself from but,
what ought to be the most prominent example
but of course be the novel Frankenstein.
Yes, which is a good novel. Yes, it's subtitled the modern Prometheus.
And probably have to remind some folks that Frankenstein is not the monster.
Oh, our contraire, Frankenstein is the monster.
Well, you know, Frankenstein's not the creation.
Yes, these two. A monster makes a monster.
steam. But what is that about? Right? It's about this person who seeks and ultimately finds this
knowledge of life and death. Yeah. How to overcome death itself. Right. And that knowledge unleashes
destruction. Right. It's knowledge that's not meant for man. Right. The man shouldn't have.
Technically, the entire over of of
that the H.P. Lovecraft is about this.
That there's just knowledge and corners of the world
that humanity was not meant to poke into.
It should just leave alone.
Although, you know, as a tech pessimist myself, right?
I connected that.
And of course, if we want very recent,
whether we're talking about Michael Criton's novel or the movies,
Jurassic Park is just a knockoff of Frankenstein.
Yeah, yeah, right. It's scientific secrets. We're gonna make life oops right
And of course
Even more recent than that
Right in terms of movies right Oppenheimer
Right the atomic bomb as we've talked about in the show
It's it's first actual use in the world was to massacre more than half of the Christians in Japan
And then I believe Father Andrew.
that within this category of examples,
you were going to channel all of your energy
into explaining why the Barbie movie is a good example.
It is.
Number one, I have not seen it.
Which I know probably some people find shocking.
But embrace your inner slave voice,
Giacca just talk about a movie you haven't seen.
We go.
But yeah, I mean, like the whole Barbie thing,
I mean, it is about this...
manipulation, right, about creating this ultimate image, you know, of, of, I mean, I never,
I never, I never played with Barbies. You know, and I'm not sure if anybody think on
the whole.
Yes, exactly. I'm going to turn off the identity, but you did. But I mean, but think about
right? And I mean, it's interesting to think about this in the sense that the culture...
And from what I can tell the movie, it's riffing on this.
The culture has now become sort of aware of Barbie
as this unattainable, unrealistic, artificial image
of womanhood, right?
And can is the kind of an accessory to that.
And from what I gather, the film and some level
is making fun of that.
So that's where you get, because now we live in everything
is the multiverse.
you get this multiplicity of bar
and Barbie World is the world where everything is perfect except it's not.
Right? And so, yeah, I mean, probably a lot of people aren't thinking of the Barbie movie as a commentary on
on this techno-mancy of our time, but from what I can tell, it kind of is.
It kind of is. You know? Didn't think we'd go there, did you listen to us?
I'll just go with it. Barb and Timber.
.
All right, all right, well, that's the end of part two.
That's the end of the second half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
We're going to take a little break, and we'll be right back with our third and final half.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF-REDIOM.
Hello, this is El Joseph Lattender. I'm happy to announce the release of my new book
when you give ancient answers and contemporary questions. In this companion volume, too,
when you pray and when you fast, I juxtapose scriptural and patristic admonitions about
arms giving with a look at contemporary issues.
make it sometimes difficult to see our way forward in this regard. Along with the rationale
for Am's giving, I offer practical suggestions for how Am's giving can work in our lives
as modern Christians. When you give is now available at store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
and father Steven DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back.
Is this the part where we talk about the Matrix?
No, it's not.
Probably not.
But yes, we're talking about the real one.
Oh, right.
This is where we, I don't know, what color should be the pill
that we give.
everyone. I don't know. I'm looking at the day.
We have to admit everyone. So it's an orange pill, the day
quill that's that I'm looking at the green pill.
It's nightquill.
See, I think day quill is just cowardice. Wow.
Nightquill during the day and fight through it.
Okay.
Be a man. That's the way to do it.
Yes. Alright.
operate heavy machinery.
forget the warning. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, so now we're going to kind of take it into the present
and ask these questions about what does this mean for us now and how we live and all this kind of stuff.
Now is where we transition to old man yelling at clouds. Indeed. Yeah. So we have to acknowledge that,
Right, like...
I admitted about myself.
You might be old. I'm middle aged.
I'm middle aged.
Why would you want to be middle aged?
I love the middle ages.
I have planned my whole life to go immediately from young to elderly.
The middle ages, sure.
But middle ages.
You're just having middle-life crises every few days?
I'm in my medieval period.
I'm just disgruntled because I don't get the senior discounts yet.
I feel like I'm getting all the bad parts of aging and none of the discounts.
the discounts.
in two years you can join ARP not that I'm suggesting you do but you can.
Oh, I will. Second, I can't trust me.
Because there are discounts that come with that. Exactly. That's why. Yeah.
It's it there. Read modern maturity. Do the word search.
It'll be great. Get your garbage coffee at the McDonald's.
That's such a great title for a magazine to modern maturity. Right. Like
They need your skull open because like I'm old but I am not mature
So for mom, I am unfortunately probably rather modern.
But yeah, so when we took that colors, we all, again, there's no view from nowhere.
And our perspective, of course, when we talk about something like technology is covered,
colored by the historical epoch in which we find ourselves.
And the sort of explosion of...
technology at the end of the 20th century. And it really is an explosion of technology.
Right. Yeah. For those of you not as old, right? I mean, I went from no such thing as an internet
to internet that you pay for by the hour to unlimited internet on a small thing in my hand.
Yeah, and I mean my favorite, my favorite on the phone timeline of development is
where we go from these things that are attached to the wall to the bag phone.
Yeah, to the cell phone, rotary phones,
attached to the rotary phones.
Yeah, before they're even touched on phone to the cordless phone to the,
yeah, but the the bag phone was a great, yeah, the big bag phone,
big giant motorola brick that you had to plug into the cigarette lighter.
You know, when I even call it a cigarette lighter now,
do they call it a power port or something?
Because no one uses it for cigarettes.
I know.
Anyway, see this is the old man yell at clouds part
Yeah, I mean I do the explosion. Yeah, my my blood eyed line used to be firmly on the other side on this side of cell phones
Like I used to say I will never get a cell phone. I don't want that kind of thing
And then I finally got like a flip phone. I got a I had a razor, you know back in
2007 finally got one
You know in my early 30s. I finally got a cell phone
The day I retire as a priest, I will no longer have a cell phone.
That's why I got one because I was working.
Yeah, you know, I have to.
Like, but yeah, yeah.
Anyway, yeah, old medieval clock.
But so the point being there was there has been objectively,
there has been a massive leap of technology in the last 40 years.
We feel it.
We feel it, right?
We feel like, especially those of us who are Gen X have seen our world's completely changed from what we were kids.
Yeah.
And.
It's different. The amount of change between 1943 and 1983 was far less. Sure. Yeah.
Then what happened in these last 40 years? Take that. But this isn't the first time this has happened though, either.
Because if you go back another 40 years, if you go to 1903 to 1943, you do have something comparable.
Yeah, I mean you go from if you're lucky, you know riding something that's pulled by a horse
to walk the course in Buggie.
Yeah.
Onobeels everywhere, radio, you know, tanks being rolled out machine guns like all of
the stuff.
Fones in your home.
Yeah.
You can call people on the other side of the country or in Europe.
Flight?
I mean, flight?
That's you.
Yes.
Yeah.
All this is what happens.
Yes.
while there has been the
This boom, it is not an unprecedented boom.
Sorry, Roswell theorists.
There have been other booms.
There was a boom at the beginning of the 20th century too.
There have been others.
Or, I mean, Gutenberg and Renning the printing press.
There's a period of time that, right?
So there have been other periods in history
where you have these technological leaps forward, right?
And then periods in between where things are relatively
stagnant or at least slower moving.
Yeah. And no one should conclude, I mean a joke about the Roswell theorist, but no one should
conclude based on what we said in the second half that what we mean is that every time there's
one of these leaps demon showed up somewhere and kind of deal with somebody to give them the
technology either. Yeah. Sometimes there are actually inventions the way that we modern
think about inventions. People sitting around tickering, figuring,
Well...
more subtle than that. Yeah, well often it's built someone's building on something
that someone else built on that someone builds off. Right. I mean someone did go the go ahead to
drop the bombs. The atomic bombs right and we're not going to say that wasn't influenced by anything
or anyone spiritually right especially the target selection. When it's get dropped primarily on
Christian communities there's something going on there right but it's not as direct as what we're
We're talking about the Apollo story or something.
Right.
There wasn't one of the Apollo hanging around
like Clinton's White House being like,
there's how to turn phyto net into this.
I was gonna say, but I remember in the weekly world news
that it said that President Clinton met on a regular basis with space aliens.
I know, but only how that issue around somewhere.
Only about 80% of what's published in the weekly world news is true.
Still read the paper.
But yeah, so the question is like it's so because we this is the question we get is this kind of knowledge evil right?
What is tech way itself? Yeah?
Is it evil the knowledge is it evil right? Yeah?
inherently
Yeah, there's certain things that you must not know yes things like HP Lovecraft right knowledge man was not meant to have right
Um, short answer no.
So, yeah, long answer, no.
Anyway, so there is not knowledge in this sense that is forbidden to humanity, period,
right?
will stop. There is knowledge that is forbidden to humanity by circumstance.
And it's that circumstance that makes it forbidden.
Yeah, like, like, I mean, and this shouldn't be difficult, everybody, especially parents,
like I have, I have a 16 year old, I have a 14 year old, I have an 11 year old and I have a six year old.
There are certain knowledge that the 16 year old, it is okay for that one to have.
but not for the six year old.
In a pro...
the circumstances are not right, it is forbidden.
Yeah, you don't go to a four-year-old and say,
everyone you know is going to die someday.
Right.
Or...
Now this is how this box of matches works.
Yes, right.
Like, which like a four-year-old, you could show them
and they could light a match.
They could get that.
You know, like they're capable of that.
As to how I know.
Right.
And right, so, so this is right, the simple cause it, but this goes even to right, go back, we're going to go back again to Genesis.
As is our want, the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, right.
You want the first story of a certain type of knowledge being forbidden.
That being violated, they're being bad consequences for humanity.
This is it.
original. Yes, yeah, this is the
were example. And this is the tree of the knowledge of good and evil. As it's described in Genesis
chapters two and three, the knowledge of good and evil is something God has.
Yeah, and God is good, purely good. He has become like us,
knowing good evil. Right. No one good and evil. Right. And the angels have it.
Yeah, right.
So, it's also in Genesis 3 where the serpent says, if you eat this, you'll become, and then
there's various ways that it gets translated, like God, like God's, or as I pointed out before
in the show, one of the earliest Old English translations of this says, like angels.
You become like angels if you eat this fruit.
Right.
And so this knowledge is an evil, this tree is an
evil tree. God made an evil tree for some reason. Right? Yeah. And this has always been understood
this way. Right? You read like again, since we mentioned it already this episode. And we don't
mention it as often as some people think. But the book of being heck, right? Right. Just constantly
talk about the book of Enoch. Wait, what? I've never done an episode on the book of Enoch. Yeah.
Other Enochic literature, other apocalyptic Jewish literature and Christian literature. When you
You have a vision of paradise.
the tree of the knowledge of good and evil is still there.
Still there, it's not cut down, you know.
It's not destroyed.
There's nothing evil about it.
The way it's been understood consistently.
And Judaism and at least an early Christianity
is that the issue was that humanity was not mature enough
to receive that knowledge yet.
not ready yet. But God created that tree and put fruit on it. So there would have come a day
when humanity was ready to have that knowledge that God and the angels already had. Yeah, it wasn't
just an ornamental tree. But it wasn't just a test. It wasn't just a random test, right?
But it was something for which humanity wasn't ready. And this is the understanding of what's going
on with that knowledge in the line of cane.
Right? It's not that learning how to make things out of metal is itself evil, right? Blacksmiths are not evil doers, right?
No.
It's that humanity wasn't ready for that knowledge that they were given that they got from spiritual sources.
And so they used that knowledge for destruction.
They used it to make war to kill each other, right? Not to make useful influence to help society, right?
Same thing with the other technology. Same thing with the atom bomb that gets used to kill a bunch of Christians. Right. There are lots of good uses for nuclear power, for example.
But all of this begs the question, and we've quoted, I believe, with St. Sephirone who said at one point, when asked about technology, asked about this burst of technology in the 20th century.
what he thought about it.
And he said if we as humans were holy or God would...
allow us to have more technology.
Because we would have the spiritual sense of the wisdom
and to know how to use it
rather than destroying ourselves with it.
But what all of this presupposes
that we may not have thought about maybe in the past, right?
Even people are familiar with the way we're talking now
because we talk that way,
St. Basil the Great talks that way.
We talk about Genesis, the Father's talk that way.
There's lots of places where...
or you can have gotten this understanding that it was an issue of maturity
with Adam and Eve that was an issue of maturity.
Angels, but this implies that there has to be some kind of,
for humanity to be, humanity to be ready requires that there has to be
some sense of the collective maturity of humanity.
Yeah, because technology is not ever a thing that's just one
person. It's a kind of, it always, it always spreads. Right. And so there's
wasn't like, well, someday you Adam and you woman or you man and you woman, you
will be mature enough that you can eat of the tree of knowledge of good and evil.
But then when your kids are born, they won't be yet. Yeah. Yeah. It's not
They'll have to wait. Right. Right.
This is an issue of humanity, right?
And it wasn't just that, oh,
Tubokane wasn't mature enough as a person to learn
metal learning.
Right?
This has to be a collective sense.
This understanding implies a collective sense of humanity,
that humanity has a collective maturation.
Okay.
And once we start thinking about that, right?
There a bunch.
of other things in terms of how the fathers read the Scriptures and within traditional
Christian theology that start to make sense because we've been taught to think about things
purely in these individual terms.
Yeah, that's because that's how our society was.
Right.
And not in these collective terms.
So for example, right, for example, it is a commonplace when talking about why Christ
was born when he was.
when you're reading the Church Fathers.
For them to talk about, and this idea is sort of forecasted in Second Temple Jewish literature,
that the history of Israel has a through line in a purpose.
That the purpose of this history that we read in the Old Testament in the Hebrew Bible
is that this pure
This remnant of Israel, most of Israel stripped away, but this remnant of Israel that's been purified. It's been tried by fire
Right and tested
This faithful remnant will emerge at the end and from that faithful remnant will emerge the Messiah
Yeah, I mean, this is what it means when it says in the scripture that in the fullness of time
God sent his son it doesn't mean that like oh the date finally arrived
you know right
Yeah, it's right. So it doesn't mean well the humans had really good roads. So the gospel could go lots of places. Well, then he could have waited till 1995 and could have gone out on the internet. Right, exactly.
Right. No, it's it's right that this purpose was and that you'll see the father's been talking about how the history of Israel culminates in the Theotokos.
Yeah, that the holiness of the Theotokos, the purity of the Theotokos.
This woman who is there to become the mother of God, the one who gives birth to God,
who gives birth to Jesus Christ, is the end product of that history of Israel,
generation after generation, being trusted and tried in finding repentance and purification,
and restoration to God, and faithfulness to God, all of that culminates in her so that she can
give birth to the Messiah.
This is why when it comes to Revelation 12, what someone asks you is that the Theotokos or is that Israel the answer is yes? Yes.
Yeah.
Porte de los dos, right?
And this is how the fathers understand it, right? That there's this through line of history.
The history is building to something, right? It is moving in a direction. Something is happening in the flow of history.
and that involves, again, a collective identity.
for humanity. This is what in St. John's Gospel when Christ promises that when the Holy
Spirit comes, he will lead you into all truth. He's not saying, well, I taught you some
stuff. But then when the Holy Spirit comes, he's going to tell you other stuff. Yeah, it's
not about information, right? Like new info, right? He's not going to tell your pastor what to
to say on Sunday even though he was planning to say something else.
Not that anyone would ever say that.
Right?
But it's that that history, this movement of history, right, isn't finished.
Isn't finished.
We don't know what it is, but there's a reason Christ hasn't returned yet.
Yeah.
Right?
There is something happening that is building toward that.
Yeah, it's not just, you know, to be continued.
It's not, we're not just...
waiting. Right. But just like in the second temple period, for example, they were looking
around going, why hasn't the Messiah come yet? Right? Because they couldn't see it from
that viewpoint. Right. After he comes, then everyone looking back on it goes, oh, that
was, that was the time. Right. That's where things were moving all along. In the same
way.
right we can look around and say why is it Christ appeared things are getting
really bad right there is a process unfolding and that is associated by
the scriptures with the Holy Spirit. This flow of history is associated
directly by the scriptures with the Holy Spirit and so the Holy Spirit is the
one guiding history particularly in and through the church right and this is
the key to understanding the orthodox.
understanding of holy tradition.
Yeah, and I, this, you know, to link back to one of our major themes, but also a particular
episode about what a spirit is, you know, a spirit, and especially the Holy Spirit who animates
the church, is, you know, it's this spirit that animates a people, that animates a group,
sometimes an individual but you know in talking about holy tradition it is this
overall historical unfolding, but it's not a deterministic unfolding. Like it's God himself is working.
He has agency. He's doing all this and sometimes you know a lot of the time we cannot see what he's
doing. Right. There's I mean like just to think about on an individual level. Not that we're talking
on the individual level, but we do experiencing it on an individual level. Like some for instance,
If someone has had a true conversion to Christ and I a lot of you listening to this have had a true conversion to Christ
You probably could not have predicted that
five ten years
Maybe one year before that happened and it's only in retrospect that you look back on your life and see how it was leading in that direction
Right that the narrative is something that's done that's apparent in retrospect
but not in the moment.
Well, this...
This is fractal.
And it's not like God is like, well, I'm working on this guy right now and I'll take care
of the rest.
No, God is God.
So he's working on every level, always, everywhere, all the time.
Which is, you know, astonishing to even begin to think about.
Right.
On a personal level, this is part of why I don't talk about my quote unquote conversion
story.
To orthodoxy.
Hmm.
It's at least part of it.
Yeah.
From my perspective now
My experience of my life is not I was heading in one direction and then there was this radical course correction
I headed in another direction. Yeah, my experience of my life is
From very early on in ways that are frankly kind of okey
God was working to bring me to exactly where I am right now
There were hints of it in weird places
Yeah, yeah
from my vantage point now, do I understand? Right? And so, like I said, this is part of the reason,
there's no point in really telling that story. I am who I am now. Right? That's the result of it.
Right? But yeah, this is true on this macro level. Right? So, tradition is not
Christ told the apostles a bunch of other stuff.
He said, hey, don't write this down.
Just when you ordain bishops later,
kind of whisper it in their ear
and they'll pass it on to the next group.
And so each generation of bishops
is sort of passed on the secret knowledge.
That's called nosticism.
Yeah.
If you think that's what tradition is in the church,
go read some say to your adeas, right?
Where he contrasts.
What goes on in the church of that?
Bricks clear.
No, the church proclaims everything.
Yeah, it's a proclimate.
Publicly as a terec secret knowledge. Yes, you just don't get it. Right. No, tradition is often defined in
or in the Orthodox Church as the life of the Holy Spirit in the church, but that's what this means.
Right. That's what this means. The historical reality of the church and our journey through the
world. Right. We believe is inspired and guided by the Holy Spirit. Right. And so that is how you
you discern.
Orthodox tradition is by looking back through the history. What writings have been preserved,
what writings have been promoted, what is Scripture, well what historically became Scripture,
right? And on and on and on. Right. And so what is the Holy Church of the Church is actually
a very objective thing. It could be good very objectively. Right. But this is the Holy Spirit.
Right.
And so we have to approach.
questions regarding technology from this perspective of human collective identity,
which is not how we tend to approach them because again, we've been taught to think as individuals,
to think about individualism. And so when the question comes up, when I go on one of my rants,
condemning social media, right, what I get as a response usually are people saying,
Well,
So I have this or that social media and here is this good thing I do with it.
Right.
Which is a very individualistic approach.
So yes, there's lots of people doing bad things with it or it's having bad effects on
lots of people, but I do this good thing with it.
But the question about technology all along, as I think we've shown, is that this collective
question. What is this doing to humanity? What is this doing to cultures to
societies to communities? Right? Because it's not that when Tubul Cain comes up with
metallurgy, no one did anything good with metallurgy. Right. It's that on the
collective whole, it was primarily used for killing.
And so we have to assess what's going on with technology and the role it's at least currently playing in terms of what is the broad effect this is having?
What is the primary use to which this is being put?
Right? And if we conclude that that is negative, that is bad.
But as we all know from a certain rule, the internet is always at least 50% pornography.
Right?
Yep.
At some point, we have to say, look, until we develop the spiritual wisdom, we plural, develop
the spiritual wisdom to employ this correctly. We need to...
move away from this technology. Right? Because no matter how many good uses I
come up to for the internet, like say doing the Lord of Sirius podcast live on
the second and fourth Thursday of the month, right? Over the internet. I'm aware of
irony here. Right? Right? The fact that your, your, your, uh,
Twin-Age Sun can look-
into Lord of Spirits on a computer in his room with an internet connection does not mean
you should put a computer in his room with an internet connection.
Because that's not most of what's going to be pumped into his room.
Yeah.
Okay.
We have to look at these broader, right, effects and these broader things, right.
for humanity as a
collective to develop the kind of spiritual wisdom necessary to do these things
has become much harder of late because we all think as individuals.
Yeah, the sense of who we are as a people or even just like who we are as a town
is getting more and more lost.
You know, like, my sense is that...
But it happened in two stages.
Like initially, we lost attention to the place that we're in and all of our attention was
on sort of like national things.
Which it's still obviously there's a big discrepancy there.
People know way more about who the president is or what's going on in Congress than they
do what's going on in their town council.
You know, really good town council affects them a lot more.
Yeah, meetings that they could literally go in a tent.
And
be heard and whatever, right? But then the next stage was, you know, because all of that
became so much just this info blast, we retreated into echo chambers and isolation. And, you
know, it's no longer like, now we mass communicate. It's like mass communication. It's funny. Like,
I've had people ask me like, can you use your-
Can you use your platform to promote this?
I'm like, you know, I don't think you understand how this works.
It's not like I have a big megaphone that everybody listens to.
I don't.
You know, we don't, right?
Like you and I could advertise something on the show,
but that doesn't make it be a thing.
You know, hopefully, you know, God willing,
we connect to the people who are listening to us,
whatever, but there's this balkanization that's occurred,
this fragmentation that's a
occurred and is getting more intense.
Somebody actually asked me earlier today,
like, I mean, they were joking a little bit,
but because there was a three week gap
between our last episode and this one,
they said, well, what am I supposed to do
about withdrawal symptoms?
I was like, go take a walk.
Yeah, that's right.
Go take a walk.
Don't listen more or whatever.
I mean, of course, I'm happy if people listen to show
or read books, whatever.
Listen to the groups.
There you go.
Which is a thing.
Yeah, yeah.
But that points to a key.
One of the main differences,
this is part of why this has gotten more difficult.
One of the main differences between the technological explosion
at the beginning of the 20th century
and at the end of the 20th century,
in the beginning of the 21st,
is that the technological explosion
at the beginning of the 20th century
primarily connected people.
Now people could listen to the same radio.
shows all over the country. Yeah, people would gather around a radio, right, in groups,
and then early television, right? Everybody was watching the same shows, right? Because
there weren't that many channels, right? And that created a shared culture, a shared
background, a shared frame of reference. The beginning of air travel, right? You could
go and see your relatives on the other side of the country more often, right? People
more connected, right? You get the interstate highway system, right? All of these things
are connecting people, creating a broader sense of community. And the more recent technological
explosion at the end of the 20th and beginning of the 21st century has done the exact opposite.
Yeah, I mean, now that there's a million choices for every person,
And I mean everybody has their own little thing.
Yeah, their own set of facts.
their own news for their own source. Like that was one of the shifts, right.
Used to be, you know, towns had two newspapers. One was Republican and one was
Democrat. Sometimes that was in the name.
Literally, right? Like they're multiple. And then when people moved to getting
everybody's getting their news from the same radio broadcast and the same TV
broadcast, that was a uniting thing.
Yeah, I mean, it doesn't mean that what gets broadcast.
Was all true and good no, it's not a great nothing subjective. We said but yeah, but there's a well
There was at least this common participation going on right. There's a common and you could argue about it
Yeah, you could say I think cronkites right on I think you could say I think that cronkites and not right like yeah, yeah
But you had a common basis for conversation
Right
Which you don't anymore, right?
Literally, people are working from different sets of facts.
Yeah, now and you can isolate yourself through the internet through the
just an echo chamber where you never hear an idea that you don't already agree with.
Yeah, where now like you know with sort of cancel culture like if I hear a thing
I disagree with I can call that a harm like I am being harmed by hearing or
being exposed to or reading a thing that I disagree with.
And not only do you block it for yourself,
but you try to get it to not exist anymore.
Yeah, yeah, but everybody right but
This is isolating. This is alienating to people right this is separating us
Yeah, and that creates this kind of feedback loop
Where we're not able to collectively come together and decide how to use this technology productively
Because the current use of the technology is pulling us apart and breaking us apart. Yeah
Right.
in this destructive way, right?
And beyond our final comment, there's no magic wand away.
That's why I said this episode isn't gonna get super happy
and happy ending.
There's not a magic wand away,
there's not an easy way past this.
No, there just isn't.
We've reached a point in terms of our lives,
our work lives, our political lives.
Right.
everything else, right, even our religious life sadly, where everything is fractured, broken
up, alienated, isolated, and all of the technology we have is just furthering that and driving
it and instrumentalizing us into being consumers until we run out of debt that we can take on,
right? That's the state of affairs.
final thoughts.
All right, final.
Centralists, it's depressing.
You know, okay.
So I have a few things to say about this.
About all this.
I mean, one thing I think that's important to point out is that
human beings are fundamentally permeable,
which means that the
isolation itself that we're using our technology for
is actually on a certain level an illusion, right?
We're still permeable. We're spiritually permeable.
And I think a lot of the time is the isolation that we're using our technology for
is an attempt to escape that.
But it creates this feedback loop. I heard I was listening to something earlier today
and they were talking about feedback loops in terms of bad behavior.
And like one of the things was said was, well, if you want to get depressed when you're
sad, isolate yourself.
And then that'll take you into depression.
And but the reality is that we're still permeable, right?
So you can put yourself within a hard bubble, but it's not really.
still perme-
to spiritual reality. And so one of the things that happens when you isolate yourself from your
fellow humans, especially when you isolate yourself from your fellow Christians, is that you're
going to be permeable to other spirits. So that's a thing that's happening. Right. And I think
that's one things that's important for us to know is that the more that we try to craft the
perfectly customized life, the more that we are going into very dangerous territory. And I think
especially for Americans.
that's a constant constant constant temptation we have to be vigilant and always correcting always
you know
Don't believe me
Go to any store that sells candy. I remember when there was one kind of Kit Kat
I don't know how many there are now I cannot tell you there's always some new combination or new version
Whatever and like I'm not saying you know don't have your your your your you know mint chocolate Kit Kat
whatever I'm just like
Think about what it does when you're constantly looking for more choices and more variety
in whatever, right?
So the other thing is, another thing is that, like I definitely agree with the idea that,
as a race, we're doing a lot of bad things with technology, right?
And yet at the same time, as you said, you know to the irony, here we are.
on the internet. I mean, this show is possible because of the internet. You're in Louisiana,
I'm in Pennsylvania. People, we had people, first there was a guy from London who said he
was listening to the guy from Uruguay, someone from Kentucky, some from Oklahoma. You know,
there's people, people all over the world and the reason they're able to listen to it is
because of the internet, right? That's a reality. And God willing, they're getting a benefit
out of it.
I don't think that that makes the way that a lot of this media fundamentally works completely
okay, but at the same time, as a preacher, as a priest, as an evangelist, as a Christian,
I know that everything that I do is going to be at least partly bad.
So I have to decide, okay, in what way am I going to participate in this world to try
to do the most good, knowing full well that I'm compromised.
Because that's just a reality.
I can't live in any other way.
We're all compromising on one level or another.
So the question is how can I do the most good
and how can I repent as much as possible.
So I do believe, I didn't believe this,
I wouldn't be working the job that I do.
That the technology can be used for good
and including internet technology can be used for good.
I see.
it in many ways as being missionaries in the marketplace. Marketplace has always been
a place of lots of temptations and a lot of bad things going on. There is the possibility
of being a missionary in that marketplace. But I think it also requires an asceticism,
an asceticism of attention and this is how we get to begin to develop a maturity with
the relation to these capabilities.
So then the final thing I'll say is,
that all of this that I just said, literally all of it, is why we always make the point on this
program. And I always make the point on all the work that I do, really. All the public work that I do
is about aiming people back to 3D parish life, right? And if you're doing that, if you're really doing it
in a very very dedicated way. You don't need any of the stuff that we're doing.
You don't need it, right?
The point of this is not to point you back to us.
Like if I say, hey, buy my book or hey, listen to this thing or hey, you know, whatever,
it's not because I want you to pay attention to me.
It's not about me.
It's about the things that we're talking about, which God willing will aim you towards a
life of real repentance in 3D, parish life, or if you're a monastic in the monastery, which
My son weird to point that out.
but actually I have met monks that listen to ancient faith radio.
When I was on Mount Dothos five and a half years ago, I met a monk who
listened to ancient faith radio.
I was kind of stunned, kind of stunned, but it's a thing.
But it's it's it's really is about pointing people back to that because
that's what the Christian life is.
It's this life of worship and arms giving and community and repentance and
love and family.
All of these things that you don't need any of this stuff to do.
But if you're out here in this marketplace with us, we're going to be pointing you in that direction.
That's always the point.
You know, if I mean, it's great if, you know, it's fine if people want to listen and like, oh, that's weird, interesting, cool stuff.
But this should not be a hobby.
Right? These things that we're talking about should not be a hobby. This should be life.
It should be life. So that's how I parse.
through a lot of this. These very difficult questions is like, yeah, we're on some level
it's always going to be imperfect and maybe even leaning very in the imperfect direction.
But still we can point people back to Christ. Father Stephen. So part of what comes out of
What we are talking about all night tonight is that the opposite.
of this kind of instrumentalization of human persons,
of their dehumanization, their alienation is freedom.
Ultimately what it is is a removal of freedom.
Part of the problem is that we've been taught to think of freedom in the wrong way,
been taught to think of freedom as individuality. This is another one of those feedback loops.
Freedom is individuality, meaning freedom is I can go and dye my hair some unnatural
color that nobody else's hair has dyed. I can go and buy. I can go and buy guns. I can
going by
drugs. I can go and do this. I can go and do that. This makes me free.
None of that is freedom.
Freedom in terms of the scriptures,
in terms of the teachings of Christianity, freedom is
freedom to serve the living God and thereby freedom to flourish.
Freedom to be human.
Freedom to be...
become the person God created you to be.
And you can't do that as an individual.
Humans can't exist alone.
Even Aristotle knew that, and he was a pagan.
Humans have to exist in community.
To be human, you have to be in a community.
That's where you become free.
Free to flourish.
But again, what we've been talking about tonight and applied...
what it is that we need to become free from once again.
There are people and powers, sometimes powers behind people,
who have instrumentalized ideas in order to instrumentalize us,
in order to dehumanize us and enslave us.
And I'm super glad that we have a disclaimer in front of the show now.
Because I can say things like what I'm about to say. I probably would anyway. But, okay.
Palestinian people need to be free.
Not free to be individuals. Not free to eat McDonald's.
They need to be free to flourish as humans.
The only way they can do that is to cast off the ideas their masters have used to enslave them.
used to enslave them.
The only way for them to be free is to cast off the ideas, the fear, the racial animosity,
the pride that have been used against them to enslave them.
People in Palestine and people will become free when they become free together.
By throwing off their masters who have pitted them against each other to their own destruction,
they say the same thing about Ukrainian people and Russian people.
But you could say the same thing about Norwegian people, about American people,
but Australian people Chinese people
Brazilian people
We are currently doing things that we don't really want to do that are making our lives
worse, that are alienating us, that we've been tricked into doing by a prolonged indoctrination
certain ideas. Lying to us about where our happiness lies.
Lying to us about what we need to be afraid of.
Lying to us about other people to keep us separated from them.
And isolated and alone which makes us better pray for the ideas that the people and the powers that have become our masters want us to do.
I'm going to end up in a similar place to where Father Andrew did.
Because the way out of this, the way to be free, we have to be free in a community. We have to be free with other people.
And frankly, the only place we can do this now is in our parishes.
The only place we can do this now is the church. There's not another spot to start building a community from.
Even if we wanted to.
There's not another place where we can come together and look at our
culture, look at our political leadership,
and I often use leadership here loosely.
Look at what we're receiving from the media,
look at it and collectively together as a community say,
you know what, no, we're not gonna do that.
We're gonna stop buying things.
Not particular things.
Not I'm gonna boycott these people
because they did XYZ.
You know what, we don't need to buy so many things.
I'm not defined, my identity isn't defined by what I consume.
That's a dumb idea.
This person isn't different from me and I don't need to be fundamentally different from
me and I don't need to be afraid of them because they're from a different neighborhood.
They immigrated from a different country.
They look different.
They act different.
They smell different.
It doesn't matter.
We can come together and collectively say that as a community.
And when we do, we will become free.
We'll experience freedom.
We'll experience more of the fullness of our humanity.
We'll be emboldened, we'll be empowered to get about the work that God created for
us to do in this world.
set free from sin to serve the living God.
is not just something that happened in Egypt under Moses,
or in Palestine in 3080 when Christ died in Rose again.
It's something that happens, has to happen for each of us.
And as many times as we allow ourselves to become enslaved again,
we need to be set free again.
Because one of the most important powers that Christ has given to us.
When he gave us the Holy Spirit is the power to break those chains of ideology, of thoughts
that bind us and try and hold us in that kind of slavery.
So that's my final thought, is that all of us need to free ourselves and we do that together.
We do that by-
rejecting the thoughts, the ideas, the ideologies that are currently keeping us from doing that and keeping us from being human together.
Amen.
Well, that's our show for tonight. Thank you very much for listening everyone.
If you didn't talk to us live, you can...
We'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordOfSpiritsandAncientFate.com.
You can message us at the Facebook page.
you can leave us a voice mail, it's SpeakPif.
and if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or need help finding a parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursday of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific,
plastic tubes and pots and pans, bits and pieces, and the magic from the hand.
And if you are on Facebook, which, as you've heard, you shouldn't be.
But if you are, you can follow our page and join our discussion group.
You can leave ratings and reviews in the appropriate places.
Most importantly, though, please share this show with a friend of yours who is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.hfafet.com.stokesupport and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
From my heart and from my hand, why don't people understand my intention?
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord.
of spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father
Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
wisdom and strength and honor.
glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.